Guide to the Martin Gardner Papers SC0647
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Martin Gardner papers
1957-1997
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Gardner, Martin
SC0647
61.5 Linear Feet
These papers pertain to his interest in mathematics and consist of files relating to his SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN mathematical games column (1957-1986) and subject files on recreational mathematics. Papers include correspondence, notes, clippings, and articles, with some examples of puzzle toys. Correspondents include Dmitri A. Borgmann, John H. Conway, H. S. M Coxeter, Persi Diaconis, Solomon W Golomb, Richard K.Guy, David A. Klarner, Donald Ervin Knuth, Harry Lindgren, Doris Schattschneider, Jerry Slocum, Charles W.Trigg, Stanislaw M. Ulam, and Samuel Yates.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Martin Gardner, 2002.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Martin Gardner was the Mathematical Games columnist for SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN from its inception in 1956 until 1986. He earned his B.A. in philosophy at the University of Chicago in 1936; after his service in the Navy during World War II, he became a writer. He is the author of more than 65 books in the fields of science, mathematics, philosophy, literature, and conjuring.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain to his interest in mathematics and consist of files relating to his SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN mathematical games column (1957-1986) and subject files on recreational mathematics. Papers include correspondence, notes, clippings, and articles, with some examples of puzzle toys. Correspondents include Dmitri A. Borgmann, John H. Conway, H. S. M Coxeter, Persi Diaconis, Solomon W Golomb, Richard K.Guy, David A. Klarner, Donald Ervin Knuth, Harry Lindgren, Doris Schattschneider, Jerry Slocum, Charles W.Trigg, Stanislaw M. Ulam, and Samuel Yates.
Mathematical recreations.; Guy, Richard K.; Diaconis, Persi; Gardner, Martin; Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-; Gardner, Martin; Golomb, Solomon W. (Solomon Wo; Coxeter, H. S. M. (Harold Scott Macdonald); Conway, John Horton.; Borgmann, Dmitri A.; Ulam, Stanislaw M.; Yates, Samuel.; Slocum, Jerry.; Trigg, Charles W.; Lindgren, Harry.; Schattschneider, Doris.; Klarner, David A.
- Game files, Series 1
  - 1/F Music, 3 folder(s)
    - 1978, April [1 of 2], 1978-1979 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents note
      MG notes.
      "Two Styles in Visual Arts: The Finitely Scaled and the Self Similar", by Benoit Mandelbrot (typescript)
      "Physical Systems with Variability on all Time Scales: Flicker Noises", by William Press (typescript)
      Correspondents:
      Sanders, David
    - 1978, April [2 of 2], 1977-1978 (Box 44, Folder 3)
      Smith, Cyril
      Mandelbrot, Benoit
    - Papers by Voss, 1984 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      Voss articles and some others
  - 24 Cubes & Austin's Dog
    - 1971, December, 1971-1998 (Box 24, Folder 18)
      Incomplete article
      Salmon, Wesley
      Klamkin, Murray
      Golomb, Solomon
      Bankoff, Leon
      Naranan, S.
  - 3-D Objects, 20 folder(s)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 1 Folder 3: Flexigons, undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
      6 hexaflexigon models (one with intertwined tie.)
      1 plastic bag with instructions to "Fortune Teller"
      1 "Meeba Teaser" (folding puzzle)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 2 Folder 2: Tower of Hanoi, undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
      Model "The Great pyramid", 9 nesting colorful pyramids.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 7 Folder 10: Bridg-it & Twist, undated (Box 55, Folder 3)
      Playing layouts and instructions for The Game of Gale (as season's greetings from the Hatchers.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 8 Folder 14: Spirals, undated (Box 55, Folder 4)
      Models of spirals
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 8 Folder 14: Spirals, undated (Box 55, Folder 5)
      Spiral drawing device - cardboard (goes with letter from Roger Hayward.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 10Folder 10: Topology, undated (Box 55, Folder 6)
      Two triangular handkerchiefs, from letter of Michael A. Pitzel. Tri-Mobius Brand.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 11 Folder 6: Bouncing Ball in Tetrahedron, undated (Box 55, Folder 7)
      Original of drawing by Roger Heyword of Stereo pair of helical chain of tetrahedra.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 12 Folder 2: Sliding Blocks, undated (Box 55, Folder 8)
      "Twice" Sliding Block Puzzle. Description: Square, 3x3, numbered sliding sub-squares: 1, 2a, 2b, 3-7, A.
      Base has pegs sticking up in 4 corner squares
      pieces have grooves in back: 2a, 4: vertical; 2b, A,: horizontal; 1, 5: both (crossing); 3, 6: none
      (The grooves in back restrict sliding over the corner squares.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 12 Folder 10: Sliding Block Puzzles, undated (Box 55, Folder 9)
      Nutzy Puzzle - plastic sliding block puzzle, 7 circle counters in figure-8 slides (slides are like a square with a horizontal line across the middle.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 13 Folder 18: Hexiamonds, undated (Box 55, Folder 10)
      1 set hixiamonds, cardboard, sealed, possibly from Niels Gottleb.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 16 Folder 4: M. C. Escher, undated (Box 55, Folder 11)
      13 Escher bookmarks.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 17 Folder 20: Pascal Triangle, undated (Box 55, Folder 12)
      Hexstat: small beads sliding in a triangular array of hexagons, to show various statistical and other relationships, from Science Materials Center. With teachers manual.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 20 Folder 13: The 24 Color Triangles, undated (Box 55, Folder 13)
      Try-Angle Puzzle, by Ora & Theo Coster. Set of 16 edge-colored triangles, 5 colors. (Jewish New Years text in colors, for Tishri 5730/Sept. 1969), plus sheet of shapes to make.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 20 Folder 20: Crossed Moebius Bands, undated (Box 56, Folder 1)
      4 velcro and zipper strips to experiment with crossed moebius band, from Jean Pedersen.
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 24 Folder 5: Pedersen's Strip Solids, Gurule's Work, undated (Box 56, Folder 2)
      GeoCube Tree Ornaments (6 fun-to-assemble ornaments), from "The Puzzle Works" (scored cardboard models.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 26 Folder 7: Napiers Bones, undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
      Paper set of "bones" - Abaco Neperiano Perfeccionada (see letter from Luis Benito Quintana.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 30 Folder 16: Non-Transitive Paradoxes, undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
      "Jen-Ken'Pon Chips", by Max Maven (a magic trick/game.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 39 Folder 4: Penrose Tiles, undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
      2 sets of non-periodic tiles (cardboard.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 46 Folder 7: Minimal Sculpture, Folded Card Paradox, 1985 (Box 56, Folder 6)
      The Ultracard Puzzle - fancy hypercard, form Gordon Jeppesen, 1985 (puzzle and magic trick.)
    - 3-D Objects: From Box 52 Folder 3: Short Problems, undated (Box 56, Folder 7)
      15 1-yen coins (for measurement problem)
  - Abacus
    - 1970, January, 1963-1973 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Accidental Patterns in Pi (& Prose Verse), 4 folder(s)
    - 1979, September, undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
      Just article, plus 1 page notes on "e" curiosity.
    - Accidental Verse, 1965-1979 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Starbuck, George
    - Intentionally Concealed Poetry in Prose, undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
      A few newspaper articles.
    - Accidental Meanings, 1967-1994 (Box 49, Folder 4)
      Lindgren, Harry
  - Advertising Premiums, 3 folder(s)
    - 1971, November, undated (Box 24, Folder 15)
      Article & Pony puzzle & Several copies of summation
    - The T-Puzzle, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 16)
      Several advertising premiums (T, L, Square) - but some are missing.
    - The Square Puzzle, undated (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Alephs II & Supertasks
    - 1971, March, 1971-1987 (Box 23, Folder 15)
      No article.
      Discussion of details of MG article by Gillman (1982)
      Gillman, Leonard
  - Anamorphic Art, 7 folder(s)
    - 1975, January, 1974-1993 (Box 31, Folder 13)
      "On conformal Transformation and it's use in Painting", by Enrique Castro-Cid (typescript)
      Anamorphic pictures of M.G., by Antonio Peticov
      Castro-Cid, Enrique
      Cerf, Genevieve
    - Slant Art, 1975 (Box 31, Folder 14)
      Various examples and reproductions
    - Amsterdam Exhibit, 1975-1976 (Box 31, Folder 15)
      Elffers, Joost
    - Kelly Houle, 1975-2000 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      Article, by Houle, on Anamorphic Art
      (Herman letters & photocopies look as if they are from another folder!)
      Houle, Kelly
      Herman, Richard
    - Cylinders & Cones [1 of 2], 1972-1975 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      Many (rather poor) photocopies of anamorphic art, and notes on phoning dealers & museums.
    - Cylinders & Cones [2 of 2], 1975-1979 (Box 31, Folder 18)
      More photocopies, etc, of anamorphic art.
      Description of method for cylindrical anamorphic projection, by Charles Kluepfel
      (Also some rep-tiles, from Jack Giles)
      Slides: 6 anamorphic drawings, J. Leupold (1674-1727)
      4 of fancy cylinders and cones.
      Mention of Scott Kim in letter to Lillian Silver (1975)
      Kluepfel, Charles
      Giles, Jack
      Silver, Lilian
    - Bibliog, References, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 19)
      Also some articles
      Amateur Scientist article, by Jearl Walker, SA, July, 1981 (cut-out pages)
      "On Brunelleschi's Perspective "Experiments" or Demonstrations", by Nicholas Pastore (preprint), It. Journal of Psychology, 1975
      "Adolf Liebig's Anamorphic Art" (news release)
      "des rebus optiques Les Anamorphoses" (photocopy) L'Estampille, Apr. 1971
      Anamorphosis: In Morphology and the Visual Arts", by Roy Behrens (photocopy) from Worm Runner's Digest, Dec. 1972
      "Anamorphoscopes: a Visual Aid for Circle INversion", by Philip Kuchel (pages) - Mathematical Gazette
  - April Fool Column, 7 folder(s)
    - 1975, April (Box 32, Folder 11)
      Note on the amount of correspondance
    - Ripoff Rotor, 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 12)
      Lots of humerous & serious correspondance
    - Da Vinci & Crapper, 1975-1978 (Box 32, Folder 13)
      Much correspondance on the existence of Thomas Crapper, newspaper articles, etc.
      Heath, Peter
      Reng, Peter
      Oliver, Barney
      McCabe, Charles
      Burnam, Tom
    - Flushed With Pride, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 14)
      Copy of the book, by Wallace Reyburn, subtitle: "The Story of Thomas Crapper", McDonald, 1969 (pb)
    - Lorentz-Contraction Paradox, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 15)
      Articles explaining "paradox"
    - e to pi times square root of 163 power, 1975-1991 (Box 32, Folder 16)
      Some proofs it is transendental, & other examples of near integers
      Devlin, Keith
      Good, Jack
      Shallit, Jeffrey
      Wrench, John
    - The Map, 1974-1977 (Box 32, Folder 17)
      Original letter and map (William McGregor)
      Suggestions on how to color maps (Bernhart)
      McGregor, William
      Bernhart, Frank
      Coxeter, H.S.M.
  - Bacon's Biliteral Cipher
    - 1972, November, 1972-1973 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Ball Bouncing Problems, 4 folder(s)
    - 1963, September (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Cube, Tetra, etc.
      "Periodic Omnihedral Billiards in Regular Polyhedra and Polytopes", by Mathew Hudelson (typescript)
      Draper, Theodore
      Knuth, Donald
      Hudelson, Matthew
    - Bouncing Ball in Tetrahedron, 1960-1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      much Roger Hayward correspondance
      Conway, John
      Hayward, Roger
    - Bouncing Ball in Cube and Hypercube, 1960-1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Gordon, Jack
      De Jong
    - Liquid Pouring (B. Ball as Computer), 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      O'Beirne, Thomas
      Mattson, H.F.
  - Bells, 8 folder(s)
    - 1978, May, 1978-1999 (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Mathematica Monongaliae #12 (May, 1971), with bibliographies of Bell & Cataan numbers
      De Camp, L. Sprague
    - Murasaki Diagrams, 1978 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Gould, Henry
      Hitotumatu, Sin
      Unger, J. Marshall
    - Bell Shuffles, 1978-1982 (Box 44, Folder 7)
      Bolker, Ethan
    - Readers on Bells, 1978-1991 (Box 44, Folder 8)
      Pratt, Vaugham
      Good, I.J.
      Sutcliffe, Alan
      James, Leigh
      Bethe, Henry
      Lenard, Andrew
    - References Bell Numbers [1 of 2], 1976-1978 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      Hoggatt, Vernon
      Pleasants, Peter
    - References Bell Numbers [2 of 2], 1979 (Box 44, Folder 10)
      Computer printout of Jeff Shallit's table of 1st 400 Bell numbers
      Golomb, Solomon (Cryptograms & Bell Numbers)
    - Gould, 1978 (Box 44, Folder 11)
      Mostly Henry Gould "Research Bibliography of Two Special Number Sequences", Revised Ed, 1976
    - Growney & Rogers, 1976-1977 (Box 44, Folder 12)
      Singmaster, David
      Growney, Jo Anne
      Rogers, Douglass
  - Bennett on Chaitin's Omega, 3 folder(s)
    - 1979, November (Box 49, Folder 15)
      "Knuth's Trivialization of Chaitin's Number as Problem Solver" (typescript)
      Bennett, Charles
      Asimov, Dan
    - Turing Machine Def. of "Randomness" (Chaitin), 1968-1977 (Box 49, Folder 16)
      Several Chaitin articles.
      Huber, Peter
      Chaitin, Greg
    - Chaitin's Ext. of Godel, 1987 (Box 49, Folder 17)
      Chaitin's articles, with reviews, commentary, & editorials about them.
  - Binary
    - 1960, December, 1959-1968 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Binary number system
  - Block Packing, 4 folder(s)
    - 1976, February [1 of 2], 1968-1976 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      Quadron puzzle description, by J. Hanny
      Foregger, Thomas
    - 1976, February [2 of 2], 1973-1996 (Box 35, Folder 10)
      "Brick Tiling and Monotone Boolean Functions", by Jonathan King (typescript)
      Klarner, David
      Brooke, Maxey
      Barnes, Frank
      Cutler, William
      Beeler, Michael
    - Ammann's and Barnes solution to all Odd Cubes, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      Ammann, Robert
      Lagarias, Jeff
    - Proofs of 7-cube Impossibility, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      Patrice, Maupou
  - Board Games, 7 folder(s)
    - 1960, April (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Shogi
      Maharajah winning strategies
      Chess variants, incl. Japan, China, Korea, Mars
      Rudge, William
      Smith, Wallace
      Blue, Richard
      Kien, Dennis
      Knight, William
    - Reversi, 1960-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      (Also called Othello)
      Newspaper article in envelope
      References, analyses, computer programs
      Knuth letter to Woodger re Bell on Reversi
      Michaelsen letter contains history
      Bell, Alex
      Michaelsen, Peter
      Carlson, Robert
      Morgan, Chris
      Brodsky, Daniel
      Peregrine, D.
      Petersen, Jon
      Ondrejka, Rudolf
      Hewlett, Clarence
    - 1963, October (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Abbott, Robert
    - Games of Black; Pathfinder, 1957-1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Original game and solution in Berlekamp letter
      Game of Black on a hexagonal board
      Description of "Reversal" game
      Smith, Donovan
      Berlekamp, Elwyn
      Eisner, Milton
      Hosken, Wesley
    - Tablut, 1960, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Berthelsen, Ingmar
      Smith, Anthony
    - The Military Game, 1960-1970 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Richard Site's solution (via D. Knuth)
      ... and others
      Van der Poel, Willem
      Gosling, John
      Simmons, Webb
      Silver, Roland
    - Focus, 19631967 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Booklet of Focus instructions, copyright Sid Sackson
      Proof first player cannot win (Yearout)
      Yearout, Paul
  - Boolean Algebra, 4 folder(s)
    - 1969, February, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      several articles and errata
    - Boolean Algebra as a Lattice, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Factors of 30, of 210, etc, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
      MG notes
    - Circuits, 1960-1970 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Article on Telephone Switching, by Feder & Spencer
      "Logical Loops", by Edward Horvath (Article) (note by Don Knuth)
      Givoli, Nachman
  - Braids
    - 1959, December, 1959-1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Group Theory
      Fox, Ralph
      Papazian, Haig
      Turner, Roseline
  - Brain Teasers - 1, 4 folder(s)
    - 1957, February (Box 1, Folder 8)
      "An assortment of maddening puzzles. Warning: The solutions will not be given until March"
    - Logician and Forked Road, 1957-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Stover, Mel
      Gummere, John
      Sciame, Dennis
      Wade, Carleton
      Janzen, H.
      Laster, Clayton
      Roubicek, Juan
      Fischer, W.
      Polakilwicz, A.
      Konikow, Robert
      Givson, Robert
      Weigle, Oscar
      Haggstrom, Warren
      Burman, S.
      Rector, Charles
      Vandegrift, Neil
      Henrickson, Patric
      Kriegsman, Edwin
      Dominguez, Loreto
      Oxaal, Gunnar
      Lewis, C.I.
      Stiles, Sam
      Morgan, John
      Goldberg, Norton
    - Cutting the Cube, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      "On the Optimum Method of Cutting a Rectangular Box into Unit Cubes", by Eugene J. Putzer and R.W. Lowen
    - Commuter and Wife, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      many
  - Brain Teasers - 2, 7 folder(s)
    - 1957, November, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Nine titillating puzzles (November, 1957)
      Also: Matematycne lamiglowki, by Martin Gardner (in Polish)
    - The 6 cigarettes, 1957-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Shifman, Jerrald
      Rybicki, Geroge & John Reynolds
      Shoemaker, David
      Burling, Robbins
      McCoy, Donald
      Gray, John
      Ceave, Hweitt
      Wierum, Carl
      Alt, Franz
      Nelson, Harry
      Klee, Victor
      ... and many more
    - Sam Loyd's Ferry Boats, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Kayser, R.
      Parkinson, Percy
      Stevenson, W.S.
    - Electrician and Wire Puzzle, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Gannett, Danforth
      Fletcher, John
      Hernandez, Rogelio
      Burton, J.
      Sammel, Goodwin
      Katz, Louis
      Stein, Phil
      Deich, Herbert
      Lebau, Louis
      Williamson, Donald
      Kassel, Louis
      Brady, Bryce
      Knowlton, Kenneth
    - The 12 Matches, 1957-1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Hejl, William
      Putzer, Eugene
      Metz, Hugh
      Hoefer, H. Carl
      Haynes, L.B.
    - 6 Inch Hole in Sphere, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Edwards, Bernard
      Bethany, David
      Job, G. Curtiss
      Rappaport, Sigmund
      Richards, Irving
      Brooke, William
      Pratt, John
      John, Brother H.
      Sholander, Marlow
      Buchanan, James
      Caffrey, John
    - Ford's Problem of the Children and House Number, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Dubner, Harvey
      Card, William
      Hartwell, Robert
  - Brain Teasers - 3, 4 folder(s)
    - 1958, August, 1958-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Carter, Geraldine
      Card, L.E.
    - Cork Plug, 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      alternate solutions and problems
      Cleveland, Forrest
      Hoard, Charles
      Klees, G.W.
      Leary, James
      Carey, Graham
      Robertson, J.S.
    - The 3 planes, 1958-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Schlosser, Jon
      Drews, P.
      Phillips, J. and Kesterson, r.
      Fineberg, Mark
      Lerner, Lawrence
      Corbato, F.
      Moruzzi, Hugo
    - Triangle Duel (3-way duel), 1958-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      also: Truel, Triel
      Schoenfeld, Gerald (also 3 planes)
      Ford, John
      Funkenbusch, W.
      Kean, Lee
      Schonblom, James
      Kloper, Kenneth
  - Brain Teasers - 4, 2 folder(s)
    - 1959, May, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Absent Minded Teller
      Long Division problem
      Wine and water
      Dividing cake
      Bronson, Nathaniel
      Houde, John
      Guskurst, Robin
      Maas, Magela
      Orr, Stanley
      McFarland, David
      Hayashi, Teru
      Gray, Dwight
      Brigham, Robert
      Edgar, David
      Argyle, P.
      Noble, William
      Kneser, H.
      Galvin, Fred
    - Desert and Truck, 1957-1994 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      "Problem in Logistics: The Jeep Problem", by Olaf Helmer, Project RAND, RA-15015, 1946
      much analysis
      Eisner, Elmer
      Phipps, Cecil
      Swanson, John
      Burchel, Robert
      Gale, David
  - Brain Teasers - 5, 5 folder(s)
    - 1960, February, 1960, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Barr's Belt
      Plane in wind
      Hair color
      (some German references)
      Macaluso, Pat
      Killian
      Gaus, Andrew
      Upson, R.
      Lubinski, Robert
    - Wife Selection problem [1 of 2], 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Numbers on slips of paper - choose highest
      "Googol" game
      various analyses (see correspondents)
      Ferguson
      Flood
      Robison
      DeBolt
      Von Nardroff
      Jackson, Robert
      Gaskel, R.
      Adams, Edward N.
      Fox
      Moser, Leo
    - Wife Selection problem [2 of 2], 1960-1999 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      "The Old Maid Problem or When to Accept an Offer", by Robert J. Heppe
      Pinkham, Roger
      Heppe, Robert
      Donaldson, Norman
    - Courier problem [1 of 2], 1960 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Sam Loyd's version of the Courier problem
      Running Dog problem
      Dog around Cadets problem
      (MG notes)
      Quartic solutions
      Graphical solutions
      Gibson
      Edgeworth
      Stout
      Shepherd
      Hinrichs, Ralph
      Neare/Rowe
      Raynor
      Wilsey, Kenneth
      Brown, D.
      Perkins, E.
    - Courier problem [2 of 2], 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      more analysis, and variations
      Green, D.
      Kress, Herbert
      Meyer, Weston
      Ehrgott, H.
      Kerst, Edger
      Hufstedler, Seth
      Meehan, Thomas
      Salsburg, David
      Keranen, David
      Brown, W.Byers
      Plice, M.
      Stoeckly, Robert
      Herrington, A.
      Younger, F.
      Hamann, Jens & Patrick Weidhaas
  - Brain Teasers - 6, 8 folder(s)
    - 1960, October (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Just the article
    - Blue Eyes, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      problem #6
      Hamilton, Laurens
      Brown, Thomas
      Kessler, Gilbert
    - Game of Hip, 1960, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Problem #1
      Merritt, Michael
      Templeton, David
      Dickensen, Allan
      Blechner, Michael & Douglas Garcia
      Andree, Richard
      Jordan, William
      Vanderpool, Donald
      Silverman, David
    - Sliced Cube and Torus, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Problem #4
      Emerson, E.
      Winker, Jean
      Bordelon, Derrill
    - Switching Puzzle, 1960, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Problem #2
      Solution in 18 with bottom sliding missing
      Flying switch solution
    - Track Meet, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Short cut solution
    - Monad, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Problem #5
      Other ways to bisect
      "Perceptual Analysis of a Symbol of Interaction", by Rudolf Arnheim, Confinia Psychiatrica 3/4 (1960)
    - Termite, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Problem #9
  - Brain Teasers - 7, 4 folder(s)
    - 1961, June, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Letters on Kant's clock problem
      Hexahedron problem
      Rook problem
      Square root problem
      Mountain problem
      Hyman, Ray
    - Arithmagic Square, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Some analysis, and references.
    - Toaster Problem, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Agricultural Materials Handling Manual, Part 1: Systems Engineering, Seciton 1.1: Introduction to Systems Engineering, Printed in Canada, 1962: contains Gantt Chart solution (p. 19)
      Davis, R.J.
      Marcus, Mitchell
      Dowd, John
      Brouse, Richard
      Johnson, Clark
      Roazen, Harvey
      Schnura, Ronald
    - 20 Question Problem, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      "Coding for the Discrete Noiseless Channel", by Solomon Golumb, 1961 (mimegraph)
      Youngblood, W.
      Zimmerman, Seth
      Johansen, Donald
      Price, Gary
  - Brain Teasers - 8, 5 folder(s)
    - 1962, February (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Article and answers
    - Placing 8 Digits, 1962-1973 (Box 8, Folder 4)